[Music]
hello you found the portal
I'm your host Eric Weinstein and this is
sort of an unusual edition of the portal
because it's coming at the beginning of
a new decade and I wanted to set some
intentions and also to sort of recap
where we've been for the last half a
year that the show has been on the on
the air and on the internet there are no
notes
there's nothing planned what I'd like to
do is to just try to speak directly
about some of the things that have been
on my mind and give you all my thoughts
on your feedback on the show and where I
think we're going to be going to next so
with with your permission let's begin
it's been a pretty interesting half of a
year the show has built up a fairly
sizable audience and what's more there
are a lot of influential and important
voices within our audience so I know
that when I'm speaking I'm reaching a
lot of the people who would be on my
dream list of people to interview to
talk to and in fact to plot next steps
with so I think we've we've had a pretty
successful run of it we can still grow
the show bigger but the show is now
large enough that I actually don't mind
losing some of our listeners and some of
our viewers by going into more
challenging topics and so I don't think
that our primary goal has is going to be
building the audience quite as much as
it was during the first six months
furthermore I think what's been somewhat
confusing is that we've had if I recall
correctly 16 different interview
episodes and one solo episode so far and
I don't think that that is exactly what
the portal was intended to be in fact
you could argue that the portal has not
even begun what we've done is to build
up an audience and to habituate
habituate the audience to a different
style of interaction I think we had to
figure out what we were going to do if
we wanted to bring you certain
high-level concepts that often get lost
because the admonition to make sure that
you don't lose your audience along the
way means that you never get very far
because you're always doing the sort
of preliminary groundwork and you're
never actually getting to the meat of
the issue and I think one of the things
that we are very proud of is that we
have a very motivated audience who's
willing to sometimes even listen to the
show more than once or do it with a
notepad so that if there are unfamiliar
concepts they can be looked up and in
fact we've noted that there have been
several communities springing up around
the show so that people can trade their
questions and we've been watching you
guys answer each other's questions in a
way that's really been gratifying so
having a lot of experts in the audience
has been a huge boon to the show and we
hope to try to figure out how to make
community in a meaningful sense a larger
part of the show on a going-forward
basis one of those efforts that's
particularly special is that we're
trying to enlist artists that can be
visual artists it could be digital
artists it could also be musicians and
the idea we have is that that Legion of
artists will be able to help push out
many of the higher-level ideas that we
would find challenging to do just in
speech by using sort of the the brains
full abilities to take in new
information and also to use the sort of
the transcendent modality to kind of
open hearts and minds to truly different
and unfamiliar ways of thinking so I
think we may try to get that going
we need obviously to build a website we
need to have some way in which people
who wish to avoid advertising can can
subscribe to the podcast and other
people who want to contribute and be
part of this as a movement we just held
our first live show at the Ice House in
Pasadena and thanks everybody who came
out the show sold out extremely quickly
even though we sort of didn't exactly
advertise where and when it was except
for cryptically at first and one of the
things that allowed us to do is to meet
the listenership on on Moss and you know
is it truly interesting and in many
different ways diverse group of people
there were pretty even split between
auntie and pro-trump voices people got
along great so we don't seem to be as
affected as I was concerned we might be
by the election cycle and what I sensed
was is that people really want to use
the show to coalesce and come together
and that there's a lot of fear at the
moment about anything tribal or anything
cult-like
and therefore anything that might be
tribal trades at a discount so I think
we might actually take a contrarian
position and decide that the show in
fact deserves more community based on
the way in which we see our our
listenership and our viewership going
and so rather than fear that anything
would emerge with leadership because all
of course anything with leadership looks
like Hitler too many people anything
that looks at all ritualistic looks like
a cult I think we're not going to worry
about those things quite so much so I
think if I can I'm going to try to
realize that in fact the audience is
leading and that I need to do a better
job of just accepting that there's a lot
of interest in new ways of thinking and
this is one way of kind of getting
unstuck to try to find the portal out of
the stasis and so if the show is to be
true to its original mission I think
we're gonna have to take some risks
which might mean drinking songs it might
mean ritualistic behavior and hopefully
it'll mean a lot more opportunities to
interact through live dates the show is
going to remain unabashedly a commercial
enterprise because otherwise it would
never happen and I want to give a huge
shout out to cast media who has been the
original studio and effectively
co-producer of the show along with
Jessie Michaels and the advertisers and
the sponsors who have been paying for
the equipment for the people who worked
on the show so that nobody had to shell
out anything in order to get this the
show would never have happened if it
wasn't taking place as a commercial and
a enterprise and so even though some of
you find the ads annoying although
others of you find them actually
entertaining or interesting
what we need to do is to come up with a
better model and a model in which
sponsors get access to the kind of heart
and passion for sticking with the show
so I think I'm gonna try to figure out
how the risk for tiser model works in
earnest this year but it's also
important to me that those of you who
wish to avoid having your brain sullied
with any kind of commercial intrusion
have an option to do that we've been
doing that through the YouTube videos
and in that respect
I feel like in general if you're willing
to sit through maybe an initial ad that
rolls before the video goes you usually
have an uninterrupted viewing or
listening experience thereafter we'll
try to get the videos a little bit and
better sync with the audio but most
importantly what I want to get to is
what the show is really about and the
last thing I will say on the sort of
initial housekeeping is we probably
needed to recognize earlier that we need
your help a lot of you guys are audio
engineers or your graphic designers or
your website builders I don't quite know
how to source the talent we need from
the pool but I've been bombarded by
wonderful offers from many of you some
of you at the absolute top of your field
who want to help this podcast because
you want to see this grow as a movement
and maybe I was slow to recognize how
genuine the interest was and just to say
thank you I mean I think it's just it's
sort of hard to recognize that it's
working for various internal
psychological reasons I've been
incredibly touched and I really want to
incorporate some of the offers of help
because lord knows we need it just
haven't figured out how to do it yet so
stay tuned I think we'll be organizing
that shortly we've now got a Facebook
group for the portal podcast we've got
an Instagram account that's growing
Twitter still our largest following but
the actual subscriptions to the podcast
on both YouTube through Apple and other
places are now quite large and I think
it'll be increasingly hard to shut down
these channels to you so that even if we
lose one or two of them because of
something we say hopefully we'll remain
engaged and we'll try to make sure that
we're we're not vulnerable to having the
oxygen cut off all right so what is it
that is happening in 2020 what kind of a
decade are we up for what's going to be
going on with the portal during the
coming year coming ten years I think
that the first thing that I want to
signal is that we are finally ready to
take on something which I have always
found to terrify and that has to do with
idea suppression now before we get to
idea suppression and how it functions
and what it is I want to take new
listeners through a very brief
description of how we would order the
world relative to the portal and its
objectives so if you will let me take
you back to the end of World War two
there's a lot of prehistory but we can't
afford to do everything so shortly after
World War Two there were two very
important events in the early 1950s
from our perspective one of which was
the unlocking of the three-dimensional
structure of DNA by Watson and Crick in
1953 and the other was the explosions of
hydrogen devices using work of Edward
Teller and Stanislaw ulam
and what that changed in the human
picture because we went from a short
period where we were dealing with atomic
bombs where Duck and Cover was a
plausible solution to dealing with
hydrogen devices in which the
destructive power was really
incalculable it's the power of gods used
to power the Sun here on earth now for
my wit to my way of thinking since the
early 1950s
there has been no comparable explosion
of wisdom to go along with this newfound
power that humans have this new godlike
power so I've called this the twin
nuclei problem of cell and atom and I
think what we've had is an incredible
run of luck and I think it's the most
magical and marvelous thing but I don't
believe that we can count on
forever and in fact given some of the
events of early 2020 taking place in
Iraq and Iran I would say that history
at the scale that we were accustomed to
it during the let's say first half of
the 20th century could start up at any
moment
and we're entirely unprepared for this
now in the story that has this major
through-line
that we've been following the next thing
that happens that's really important is
a guy named Eric de sola price starts to
calculate that science is on an
exponential trajectory and rather than
thinking that that's a great thing he
starts to understand that anything on an
exponential trajectory can't really go
on because it's going to burn itself out
and if science is the original seedcorn
if you will of technology and technology
of economics then effectively what's
going to happen in science is going to
percolate through a chain through
technology and into the economy with a
potential stagnation coming now he
started to arrive at these ideas I think
at Yale in the late 1950s it was not
well understood what he was talking
about and still I always shocked that
the book science since Babylon which he
wrote and which discusses this issue is
so much less well known than say Thomas
Kuhn structure of science scientific
revolutions for some reason this is so
dispiriting to so many people that we'd
actually don't discuss it much studying
this work led to the idea of talking
about egos that is embedded growth
obligations now embedded growth
obligations are the way in which
institutions plan their future
predicated on legacies of growth and
since the period between the end of
World War two in 1945 in the early 70s
had such an unusually beautiful growth
regime many of our institutions became
predicated upon low variance technology
led
stable broadly distributed growth now
this is a world we have not seen in an
organic way since the early 1970s and
yet because it was embedded in our
institutions what we have is a world in
which the expectation is still present
in the form of an embedded growth
obligation that is the pension plans the
corporate ladders are all still built
very much around a world that has long
since vanished we have effectively
become a growth cargo cult that is once
upon a time planes used to land in the
Pacific let's say during World War two
and indigenous people looked at the air
strips and the behavior of the air
traffic controllers and they've been
mimicking those behaviors in the years
since as ritual but the planes no longer
land well in large measure our
institutions are built for a world in
which growth doesn't happen in the same
way anymore
all right what then happened was is that
a different structure which I have
termed the gated institutional narrative
came to become repurposed now the gated
institutional narrative is like an
exchange a financial exchange if you
will except it's an exchange of
information and ideas and in order to
actually participate in this particular
special conversation you need to have a
seat on the exchange that is you need to
write for an important paper like The
Wall Street Journal or you need to be a
senator or a congressman so that you can
gain access to the news media where you
need to be sitting at a news desk
in any of these situations whether
you're a professor or a reporter or a
politician if you can gain a seat inside
of the gated institutional narrative you
can attempt to converse with other
people within that particular
conversation the rest of us do not
really have the same level or kind of
access to this highly rarefied
discussion and I've previously compared
this to what we would term a promotion
inside of the world of professional
wrestling
it's an agreed-upon structure in which
people
often agree to simulate dispute rather
than actually have disputes because
somebody could get really seriously
injured but they're in fact working
together to produce a an engaging and
regular product for mass consumption the
problem with this gated institutional
narrative is that in general it doesn't
contain the most important ideas and
that is where the gating function comes
in the most important ideas are likely
to be the ideas that are most disruptive
what if the entire food pyramid for
example was wildly off what if fats were
not the great danger we thought they
were
and those waving fields of wheat that
are fabled in American song in fact give
rise to carbs which are very dangerous
to us all so if everything were inverted
let's say we're in a world where instead
of banishing my volatility during the
so-called Great Moderation before 2008
we were actually building the tinder for
the world's largest financial forest
fire what if in fact we had all sorts of
things exactly backwards and completely
wrong
what if diversity wasn't always a sign
of our strength but sometimes a sign of
our weakness what if for example
immigration far from being an issue of
xenophobes
versus zina files was actually an
instrument of redistribution having very
little to do with xenophobia or zina
philia to begin with these sorts of
ideas can't be entertained inside of the
gated institutional narrative and that's
where the gating function comes in what
was originally a function intended to
ensure quality control of the narrative
became an instrument for something else
and this is where I want to introduce
the most important concept that I think
we will be dealing with on a
going-forward basis in 2020 on this
program the disc
what is the disc the disc stands for the
distributed idea suppression complex now
taking it apart the center of it is idea
suppression not all ideas are good and
so idea suppression is very frequently
understood
as an important concept when we're
talking about something like bigotry or
we're talking about something like
violent ideology of course we want to
suppress certain ideas but these are not
the ideas that are principally important
inside of the disk the disk is actually
a complex it is a large collection of
different structures and it's not
controlled in any one place
many of these have emerged separately
but what makes a aspect of the disk what
shows you a particular component is that
it protects institutions from
individuals who are making valid and
reasonable points so if you imagine that
the institutions have become incredibly
fragile because they're in fact built
for growth and that plan for their
growth if it obligates them to tell
untruths and to hide certain
characteristics because they are not in
fact able to grow at the rates in which
they are supposed to you need some
complex for making sure that that
information doesn't reach the bottom
entrance to a pyramid structure let's
talk about some aspects of idea
suppression the two stories that I'm
following most closely and we can date
this particular episode by talking about
current events I think that's fine the
two stories I'm following most closely
with interest from the perspective of
understanding the disk are the story of
Andrew yang and the media and the story
of Jeffrey Epstein and his recent demise
now in neither of these cases is my
principal interest the ostensibly
subject matter in the case of Andrew
yang Andrew is going through a weird
ritual that I've noted repeatedly
election cycle after election cycle
perhaps the most three recent versions
of this situation have been with Ron
Paul in his run for president with
Bernie Sanders and his run for the
president
see and now with Andrew yang in all of
these cases we see a very bizarre
behavior inside of the news media that
is that when the candidate starts to
gain traction with the public they
become left off of lists they become
misreported very often a reporter will
stand in front of the graphic that has
that particular candidate alongside
others and we don't really know why this
is occurring and we don't know how these
instructions are going out but in the
case of Andrew yang because this is
taking place in a highly connected
Internet era we have people chronicling
all of the myriad ways in which Andrew
Yang's candidacy is distorted in
particular there appears to be a
different level of distortion taking
place at one particular news media
outlet we need to better understand
exactly what is the political economy of
the news now in the case of Andrew yang
the key question would be why aren't the
regular news media and the competing
news media reporting on the outside
effort being made to make sure that
Andrew does not appear normally with
other candidates in this Democratic
primary field it doesn't make logical
sense if you believe that the principal
reason for reporting on the election is
to make sure that the voters have an
early opportunity to hear all voices and
to begin to make their decisions rather
than immediately trying to pick a
narrative about frontrunners who are
always taken to be inevitable and that's
a conserved feature of this bizarre
election coverage cycle after cycle so
the first thing I want to do is
recommend that you google MSNBC and
Andrew Yang and yang media blackout and
look at the impressive data set that has
been collected which shows a singular
focus that can be inferred from the data
on Andrew yang now to an extent this has
also happened with Tulsi Gabbard to an
extent this is
there's been a some carryover from
Bernie Sanders but Bernie Sanders
showing in 2016 was so strong that the
same games that were applied to Sanders
then cannot easily be applied now but
the key question we have is why is the
news media spending so much on one
candidate who doesn't appear to be that
large to keep that candidate from
growing I think this is an interesting
topic and what it has to do with is
making maps of silence now through the
efforts of Dana Boyd and the data and
society group we've learned about a
doctrine called strategic silence and
that is that there are certain things
that the media may not want to happen
and therefore rather than simply
reporting the facts of the matter
they make editorial decisions so as not
to give fodder or fuel for some
undesirable outcome now we can partially
understand that in the case of copycat
killings out of after let's say gun
massacres but it's much harder to
understand why somebody coming from
outside of the political system would be
treated to something like strategic
silence or strategic distortion what we
need to do is to have a better
understanding of the maps of silence and
maps of distortion that take place in
our press and what andrew has done that
is special and unique is that he's given
us a very large n for our data set we
now have enough different incidents of
this that we can begin to piece together
what make might be inferred from this
very bizarre behavior the second example
of this that I find fascinating is the
death of Jeffrey Epstein now you'll hear
a lot of other people say well Epstein
didn't kill himself or it's obviously
this or it's obviously that I have a
decidedly smaller interest in those
questions the questions that fascinate
me have to do not with Epstein not with
who might have killed him whether he
died by his own hand but they have to
deal with the sense making apparatus
that is the news media around this
untimely exit from our world now Jeffrey
Epstein was accused of trafficking and
had a very bizarre lie
that is difficult for many of us to
understand where he got a slap on the
wrist in Florida and appeared to operate
with impunity even after his conviction
in Florida as a sex offender what's
fascinating is that if anyone remembers
the Watergate era the news media used to
go to federal agencies and ask whether
or not something was true or false and
this gave us the phrase a non-denial
denial when the question arises let's
say in this case does Jeffrey Epstein
have any ties to any known intelligence
community that question can be asked
let's say to the CIA to the State
Department to the NSA and you might
expect that you'd get an answer
absolutely this person had no ties
because the the idea of the intelligence
agencies being connected to a known sex
trafficker seems preposterous at one
level but you could also imagine that
they'd get no comment now we don't even
have that in the situation you can go I
think I did this fairly recently with
the New York Times and tried to simply
use their own search engine have you
asked the question whether Jeffrey
Epstein had ties to the intelligence
agencies the other questions that arise
in this case are Wenner is the last
known recording of ghilane Maxwell's
passport crossing a border this is a
simple factual question a reporter would
be dispatched they would call up
somebody like Interpol they would try to
find out whether people would speak
about it or not speak about it in under
any circumstances they would be able to
print an interesting story for example
Interpol has no comment or Interpol says
that the last recorded border where
ghilane Maxwell's passport was showed up
was you know a border crossing in in New
York City under any circumstances it is
very bizarre to see the map of silence
around these questions another such
question is if
geoffery Epstein's fortune came from
currency trading where are the records
from his office in Villard house in
manhattan he had a very large office in
a trophy property on the island of
Manhattan and to the best of my
knowledge I have seen no printed
discussion of where the supposed trading
records of this person who seemed to
amass a fortune another weird thing
about this fortune is is that he seemed
to live life as a high 11 figure
individual owning islands and incredible
properties in multiple jets and yet all
of the assets I've seen accounted for
puts him in stead in nine figure
territory now that's two orders of
magnitude difference and I don't think
that there are many nine figure rich who
would live anything like Jeffery
Epstein's lifestyle it appears that most
of the assets were put towards a kind of
front if you will so we don't have any
idea about where the records are of his
trading we don't have any idea where the
passport of his partner was seen last
and we also have no confirmation that
any of our major government agencies
have denied the Jeffrey Epstein the
accused sex trafficker was tied to any
Intelligence Committee community in all
of those situations which you can map
with honesty and without having to go
anywhere near tinfoil hat territory is
that there's something broken with our
sense making apparatus because in the
Watergate era you could have assigned
this to a cub reporter and they would
have known exactly what to do where are
are no comments on the record no one
knows all right in those two
circumstances that gives you an idea
about how the disc the distributed idea
suppression complex works inside of
journalism there is some sort of
editorial function that is keeping us
from learning certain things because
certain stories do not run
with a little bit of poetic Liberty this
seems to be what some Paul Simon was
talking about in Sounds of Silence what
we're listening for now are the silences
where else are we confronted with
silence what are the other things we
would expect where we don't hear
particular ideas now obviously you have
a situation where I've been talking for
quite some time about the idea that
there are many reasons that one might
ask to restrict immigration the Sierra
Club used to support a restriction of
immigration farm workers unions used to
support restrictions on immigration but
sometime in the fairly recent past
it became a et fix of the elite that the
only reason for supporting a restriction
and immigration the only possible reason
could be that you were xenophobic and
probably racist now I don't exactly know
where these ideas came from but I know
that these ideas are prima facie I'm
preposterous they make no sense and so
I've been talking for some time about
where are the media willing to discuss
all of the reasons that one might want
to restrict immigration having nothing
to do with xenophobia the so-called
zina philic restriction espect 'iv this
is another place where there is no
public discussion and we have no idea
why so once you begin to look for these
silences these gaps you start to become
rather terrified that somehow the world
is not behaving properly and that's one
of the reasons the people are flocking
to this podcast this is however not my
major focus my major focus of the
distributed ideas suppression complex or
disc has to do with what happens inside
of our universities now I'm in a
somewhat unusual position in that both
myself and my wife have PhDs as well as
my brother and his wife and we've all
appeared in interviews within the last
five years so maybe you've seen all of
us on camera or have some idea of how
Brett Weinstein Heather huiying p.m.
Milani and I sound what some of you
don't know
is that I believe that inside of that
group of four one of us wrote a book
immediately after getting a PhD which is
Heather Heinz book antipode about her
solo travels to the jungles of
Madagascar so if you have a young woman
in your life who's looking for a pretty
impressive female role model I would say
Heather's toughness intelligence and
grit makes for a pretty terrific reading
and I'd recommend buying the book
antipode for that for that young lady in
the case of the remaining three none of
us wrote a book immediately afterwards
however I think that the quality of the
discoveries that were being explored was
incredibly high and in each case what I
thought happened to those was most
unexpected now what are these ideas that
are I'm claiming were suppressed so I
would say that in one case we were
talking about the reasons why we died
one of these theses contained what I
think is one of the best models for the
reasons that we have these finite
lifespans and of course we're all
subject to what might be called
environmental insults if a piano falls
on your head while you're walking down
the street that's usually going to be
your exit but why we age why we get
cancer and why we die I think has not
been very well understood at the
molecular level and I I think perhaps
one of the first mature attempts to do
this took place in my brother's thesis
at the University of Michigan this is
one of the major ideas that I wish to be
exploring in 2020 if biology is one of
the greatest ideas man has ever had in
the form of natural and sexual selection
and the work of Darwin and Wallace I
would say that the other complex of
great ideas truly top ideas would be
what I would call geometric dynamics
those are the ideas that take place
underneath theoretical physics whether
we're talking about
the standard model or general relativity
now we now believe that all fundamental
physical phenomena can be divided
between these two great theories in one
case that of Einstein's general
relativity it's been known for about a
hundred years that the substrate of the
theory is Riemann's theory of
differential geometry that is Rahmani in
geometry what is much more recent
perhaps slightly less than 50 years old
thanks to Jim Simons and CN yang is the
notion is the knowledge that the
classical theory underneath quantum
field theory is in fact a different form
of geometry known as eros Monte and
geometry fiber fiber bundle geometry
gauge theory or you know steam rod
geometry whatever you want to call it so
the idea the geometry is the birth place
of fundamental physics I think is now
generally understood by all practicing
theoretical physicists functioning at
the top level inside of that complex
we've been stuck for approximately I
don't know forty seven years where
Theory used to lead experiment and we
used to make predictions and the
predictions would usually be confirmed
in relatively short order we have not
had a period of stagnation inside of
theoretical physics that mirrors this
with the closest comparable period
perhaps being the period from the late
1920s with the advent of quantum
electrodynamics to the late 1940s with
the beginning of renormalization Theory
being ushered in at the Shelter Island
Pocono and oldstone conferences so that
20-year period is now more than doubled
and we haven't been making progress and
I've been very uncomfortable with the
idea of coming forward with ideas why
well to be honest it's very rare for
anyone outside of theoretical physics to
have reasonable ideas in physics I could
explain why but the physicists are
fantastic they've got
all sorts of no-go theorems and all
sorts of considerations that have to be
kept in mind and effectively what
they've got is a world that is so
tightly constrained when it comes to
understanding where we are that almost
every new idea is instantly dead on
arrival now this has been incredibly
demotivating to people in the field and
it does feel from many different
perspectives like we're almost at the
end if not of all of physics at least of
this chapter of physics but what I'm
starting to see is that the field has
become exhausted it has been telling the
same story since 1984 about how string
theory is our leading theory of quantum
gravity that quantum gravity is the
replacement for Einstein's search for a
unified field and as the accelerator
turns up the Higgs and little else as
effectively no new physical theories
arise with confirmations as the only
major updates to our model of the
physical world are things like massive
neutrinos or the accelerating expansion
of the universe coming from experiment
the theoretical physics community has
been very slow to own up to just how
much trouble it's in it's an incredibly
demanding life it has incredible
standards for rigor and intellectual
honesty and quite honestly it's been
lying for far too long to sustain the
kind of integrity that's needed in that
community now I don't know whether I'm
nuts but I do know that at previous
points I've suggested things into the
both the mathematical and physics
communities that have later been shown
by other people to be correct and while
I was waiting for some kind of
confirmation I was being told Eric
you're completely off-base you're not
getting it one of these situations
involves something called the cyborg
Witten equations which I put forward in
the 1980s ran probably 87 and I was told
that these couldn't possibly be right
that there they weren't sufficiently
nonlinear I'll tell the whole story
about how if spinners were involved and
obviously Nigel Hitchens
would
told us so blah blah blah none of this
was true and in 1994 natty sai burg and
edward witten made a huge splash with
these equations I remember being in the
room and seeing the equations written at
MIT on the board and I was thinking well
wait a minute those are the equations
that I put forward if those equations
are being put forward by Witten why is
it that the community isn't telling him
that they're wrong for the same reasons
they told me that they were wrong this
is also how idea suppression works when
you were young and when you are
vulnerable and when you need the help of
older members of your academic community
to bring you forward you're extremely
vulnerable to what might be termed the
droite de senor of the academic
community now for those of you who
aren't familiar with it or the Prima
notte there was an old legend that the
lords of the manor would command the
right to take the virginity of every
bride on her wedding night until there
arose a miller's daughter known as the
mug nya and the mug nya had a different
plan for she wished instead to be with
her husband and not the evil lord of the
manor so what she did was she smuggled a
knife underneath her robes and appeared
in the bedchamber of the lord of the
manor and killed him now this is
celebrated in the festival of the
oranges which is potentially the world's
largest food fight in which armed
combatants throw oranges at each other I
think it's in Italy if I'm not mistaken
celebrating the victory of the mug nya
but right now we have a problem in our
intellectual disciplines which is that
when we come forward with our best ideas
very often even if they're slightly
wrong they're slammed and when they're
slammed sometimes the the older members
of the community then take the ideas for
themselves at a later point this has to
stop and I think I've been trying to
gather courage to put forward some ideas
which I think some of them some aspects
of them may be wrong but are certainly
quite interesting and given that our
leading theories have completely stalled
out and failed to ship a product for
depending upon how you count
you know nearly 40 years or 50 years
depending upon whether it's the anomaly
cancellation or something called the
vanetti on a model I think it's time to
simply ignore these people and realize
that the leading lights of our most
important community have failed if we
don't figure out the full source code
going beyond Einstein going beyond the
standard model we can't know whether
we're actually literally trapped in our
local area or whether we have some hope
of going out and looking at the night
sky with an idea that that might be the
roadmap to our future so whether or not
we're consigned by Einstein to the Elon
Musk program let's say of exploring the
Moon and Mars or whether in fact we
might get on the Star Trek or Star Wars
program of exploring the cosmos has to
do with whether or not we can get the
source code so the next thing has to do
with who we are what is this place and
what I've called geometric unity it is
the aim of making the portal a place
where I can have a channel that cannot
be controlled by the academic complex
and I'll come back to that in a second
the third area that I want to talk about
has to do with markets now markets are
really the sponsor of our freedom by
having non centrally directed locally
organized human activity free agents are
able to contract freely with each other
exchange with each other build
prosperity lift each other up and if you
are a progressive you almost certainly
really have to appreciate the power of
markets but our markets are in great
danger at the moment in my opinion
because they are being meddled with and
they are returning results that indicate
that only a tiny fraction of us are
worthy of reaping the true rewards of
the markets while many of us feel that
we're being left behind if you look at
the wealth structure of the Silent
Generation boomer generation Generation
X and the Millennials are Gen Y you see
that the Millennials have at this age
massed far smaller percentages of the
wealth than the Boomers did the same
and I don't think it's because they're
lazy or they're not talented so we have
a very dangerous situation shaping up
where our younger generations are not
fully bought in in fact in the last year
I just bought my first house I'm 19 I'm
54 years old born in 1965 I bought one
car and then had to rebuy it went ahead
and it got rear-ended there's something
very bizarre about that pattern for
somebody who was educated at an Ivy
League undergraduate institution and has
an advanced degree from potentially our
leading institution in the country we've
created a world in which it's simply too
hard for regular people to advance
properly because the society is not
growing now rather than complain about
it I'd rather do something about it so
partially what I hope to do is to show
you what's been going on with GDP and
inflation by introducing a new theory
that combines the two greatest theories
we have so if you think about biology is
being driven by the theory of natural
and sexual selection and if you think
about physics is being driven by
geometric dynamics either coming from
riemann or Aris money in geometry then
in fact what would be the the meeting
place of our two greatest theories the
only place that I'm aware of is that it
takes place in economics and why is that
because you have Apes carrying on the
theory of selection but by other means
through markets and what are markets
markets are an attempt to create and as
if physical system by uniform izing
apples and oranges so that we have a
basis for their comparison by using
mediums in exchange like money so in so
doing economics is the logical meeting
place for the two greatest theories man
has ever had and this was explored in
the early rather the mid 1990s early to
mid 1990s by Pia Milani my wife and
collaborator and myself in work that
never got out of Harvard University
that's not quite true there is a book
called the physics of Wall Street by
James Weatherall which touches upon this
but
this work died because of something
called the Harvard job market committee
and my wife went into that job market
committee meeting having her work
presented there thinking that she could
apply anywhere in the country and being
told instead that she had almost nothing
and that should be lucky to escape with
the PhD now in these three cases that is
a theory of death that comes out of my
brother's work at the University of
Michigan a theory of productivity and
how our wealth is inflated away coming
out of my wife's work at Harvard and
another theory about what is this place
and how do these different geometries
come together which would be the subject
of geometric unity all three of these
ideas met a level of resistance that
none of us had ever anticipated or
encountered and I think it's been
terrifying to me to think about the idea
of going up against the institutions
however last year I made an interesting
calculation I decided to look at the
presidencies of all of our leading
research institutions and to try to
figure out how many of them belonged to
people who came after the baby boom in a
previous world let's say the world of
the early 1980s approximately half of
the heads of research institutions would
be Gen X and Gen Y that is Xers and
Millennials however almost no research
university certainly almost no leading
research university with I think the
exception of the University of
California at Berkeley when I did this
calculation last year was under anything
other than the presidency of a baby
boomer now what had happened well we got
rid of a mandatory retirement
requirement that probably affected
things fairly significantly and we began
to concentrate all sorts of power in one
generations ideas now generations aren't
magical things what they are are instead
cohorts that are exposed to some set of
circumstances that is peculiar to the
time in which they are growing up
so for example if your primary
experience is that you work hard as a
kid with a paper route and an internship
you go to college you work your way up a
ladder and everything works out fine and
pretty soon before you know it you've
got three kids in two homes that's your
idea of what a normal life is now this
is sort of the basis of the meme okay
boomer because many of the rest of us
who followed this generation have no
idea how you would accomplish that in
these times I actually put the blame
slightly more in the Silent Generation
than most people do I think if you look
at it you realize a lot of the problems
that we're going that we're having now
began through intergenerational issues
initiated by the silence rather than the
boomers but it's a pretty stark division
between the Xers Millennials and Gen Z
and the silence and the boomers as the
major generations that are still extant
in this situation it's terrifying to say
what I'm about to say next but it is
time to inflict ourselves on our own
institutions it is time to have Gen X
candidates for presidencies not
necessarily just of the political
parties because we've spent what is it
20 years on on men born in the summer of
1946 so far I mean we're just at the
beginning of baby boom presidencies and
we've been doing it since 1992 that
doesn't make a lot of sense on the other
hand I think that the presidencies of
companies or CEO roles I think that the
issue of university presidents many of
these things have been tilted far too
much towards these other generations I
think that Gen X has a very interesting
story to tell we were not highly
infantilized in terms of when we were
growing up in fact we had the moniker of
the latchkey kids and we're also not
large enough to get things just by
chanting them we have always had the
pressure of having to make some degree
of sense because we're just too small as
a generation so in fact what I'd like to
do I've
said that I believe that string theory
is effectively an affirmative action
program for mathematically talented baby
boomers who do not wish to sully
themselves with the problem of working
on the physical and real world as we
have what I'd like to do is to bring you
these three theories over the course of
the next year or two that is a theory of
death a theory of markets and how the
agents within those markets and the
measurement of those markets should be
changed and understood and a theory also
about who we are and what is this place
in which we find ourselves called
geometric unity the purpose of the
portal if you will is to create a
channel that has never existed now I
could try to submit everything to Fizz
review of letters I could try to submit
to econometrics I could try to go
through all of the normal channels and I
think what I've started to realize is
part of the problem of having screwed up
all of this early stuff in our lives of
having tried to do this the formerly
formal and right way so to speak the
privilege of having been screwed over so
directly and so beautifully by the
system is the right to raise the middle
finger to the institutions like how dare
you expect that I'm going to use your
quiet procedures if you think about what
peer review is it's the exact opposite
of what peer review should mean peer
review should mean that you publish your
article and then the peers in the
community review it but in fact what it
is is peer suppression you take your
article and you mail it off to somebody
who you don't know that person gets an
early look at it they might hold it up
in review they then inflict any changes
that they want or they reject it for
reasons that make no sense and then it's
handed back to you now why does it have
such a positive spin it's not
long-standing in the community it
doesn't seem to have a very long history
but it came out of an effort to Quality
Control new ideas we wanted to know if
new ideas were coming from
reputable people were they using
reasonable methods were they reasonably
familiar with their fields and in fact
that is the good reason that we had this
new technique of peer-review previously
editors had been tasked with being
responsible for the field and figuring
out whether or not something was up to
snuff in this new situation
it was perfectly constructed for abuse
in fact what you find is that it's like
what my brother refers to is the low
posted speed limit in a southern town
the key question isn't peer review its
how is it enforced for different people
that is if you are a famous professor
who is well plugged into a journal where
your friend is the editor you're going
to have an entirely different experience
with peer review and if you submit the
exact same article coming from someplace
that is not well-known to that journal
and in which there is a bias against
that group for example if I were to
point out that every purebred dog in a
kennel show is a product of intelligent
design that is that humans have
commanded canines with whom and how they
can mate that process has produced
things like dachshunds and poodles
however if I use words like intelligent
design I guarantee you that even though
it's clearly true that dogs are
intelligently designed that that paper
will be rejected because there is a
belief that we should have a line which
says no paper on intelligent design has
ever been accepted by a leading
peer-reviewed journal now that political
understanding of intelligent design has
to do with both a reasonable idea and an
unreasonable idea the reasonable idea is
that you should not be able to smuggle
Jesus into evolutionary theory you
should not be able to do young Earth
Creationism inside of a scientific
context that is the previous reasonable
version of Intel peer review and makes
sense as quality control
but what happens when you start talking
about perception mediated selection for
example pseudo copulation in orchids
which we've discussed before or in the
predatory system with the muscle lamp
bacillus where the perception of the
bass matters because it thinks that it's
consuming a bait fish but in fact that's
a fake bait fish filled with the young
of the muscle in both of those cases you
have perception mediated selection and
you could make an argument that that
should be called intelligent design but
those magic words can't appear in that
journal why for a political reason so
what we have is we've created a system
based around quality control that in
fact is rife and open for abuse in that
system we now have to realize that we
need other channels we need an ability
to route around we need to be able to
reinsert dissidents and people who do
not get along with institutions back
inside of the institutions if you look
at Noam Chomsky sitting at MIT you will
realize that it was once the case that
such people were much more common you
can look up a fellow an old friend of
mine named Serge Lange and you could
scarcely believe that such a person
could have existed at Yale but the but
that person very much did exist you can
look at an old controversy about David
Baltimore and a woman named Margot
O'Toole and the courage of Mark potage
me and Walter Gilbert in fighting a
Nobel laureate when Margo O'Toole
accused a colleague of the Nobel
laureate of misconduct or at least
reproducibility of results we have a
long and storied history that has gone
wildly off the rails with the crisis in
current sense-making and the purpose of
the portal was always to set up a
channel by which we would have enough
people watching that we could attempt to
keep people from being rolled in the
alleys when they contradicted the
institutions and that is in large
measure what we're here to do if you
look at our episode with Tim or Quran we
introduced you to a concept of
preference falsification right now the
danger of
the Andrew yang and the Jeffrey Epstein
situations is is that they have
conveniently communicated to many people
of course we're going to mess with your
sense making what is it you're prepared
to do about it
this brings us to a final issue which i
think is incredibly important which has
to do with why there are no living
heroes in effect we almost don't believe
in heroism as soon as somebody starts to
make us excited about the world and what
is possible for the individual we come
to start feeling terrible about that
person unless there's trapped inside of
a Marvel movie or something like that if
you go back to the history of ticker
tape parades you will see that there
were many ticker tape parades given for
individual aviators individual explorers
ships captains who put their ship at
risk to rescue the crew of another and
in fact this pattern were largely
stopped my contention is that the
difficult case of Charles Lindbergh may
have marked a turning point in
Lindbergh's case he had flown solo to
Europe from the United States and come
back a hero I believe in the late 1920s
now Lindbergh was a very difficult human
being to deal with because he was an
authentic hero and he was also somebody
who believed in America first and in
isolationism and given the Nazi Menace
in Europe I think that's almost an
unforgivable position nevertheless the
fact is that Lindbergh commanded to
tremendous popularity and that
popularity could have been used to keep
the u.s. out of a war what I find is is
that since Lindbergh it has been very
rare to elevate any individual to the
point where they can oppose our
institutions the Pete Seeger's and
Albert Einstein's of the world who
fought against McCarthyism were a huge
danger to the industry that was cropping
up around anti-communism when it came to
the Vietnam War it was very dangerous to
have popular entertainers like John
Lennon who were against it
we have been frightened about
individuals
coming to rival our institutions in
terms of power and that's what's so
great about the new revolution in
long-form podcasting and all of these
other forms of social media now we have
a great danger in that most of these
platforms are mediated we saw what
happened to Alex Jones it's quite
possible that if these powerful
institutions come to believe that a
particular individual should be removed
they can always choose to enforce the
rules in a different way we saw recently
the advent of Terms of Service changes
in to include dead naming now if I say
that Walter Walter Carlos composed the
album switched-on Bach or perform the
album switched-on Bach that is a true
statement but because Walter Carlos
became Wendy Carlos I have no idea
whether or not I can be accused of dead
naming imagine that you have a hundred
such rules rules that are never spelled
out never clear that can be enforced any
which way to deny someone access to the
major platforms this is the great danger
with this moment we have unprecedented
access but we also have a gating
function which can be turned on at any
time if we fall out of line with the
institutions I want to read you one
tweet that has been on my mind for quite
some time this tweet came from a
contributor to The Washington Post who's
a professor at the Fletcher School and
it said good morning Eric I'm gonna
leave out the parentheses so I've read
up on a few of your notions and I have
some thoughts but my basic conclusion is
simple
what's true isn't new and what's new
isn't true I think it's fantastic I was
stung by it because at first I was under
the impression that we were still living
in a world in which the Washington Post
New York Times Harvard Stanford
what-have-you
control the major conversation but
coming off of a recent date at the Ice
House in Pasadena which was a live gig
with Peter Thiel I've started to realize
how powerful this new movement is we can
reach anyone anywhere what I now believe
is that the
gated institutional narrative has been
spoiling for a fight we are quickly
coming to the point where we have a
David and Goliath moment we now need to
try to re-inflate the individuals who
are uncorrelated who are not
particularly good at taking orders who
don't like committee meetings who don't
want to sign a oaths but who were
passionately committed to the public
good and to some version of intellectual
meta honesty we need these people to
once again take up positions inside of
the institutions and I would like to in
fact inflict myself on my favorite
institution Harvard University the
children of Harvard University have
always been divided into white sheep and
black sheep and there's no question that
I represent black sheep Harvard but I
also think that one of the features of
the university that makes it's great is
that it has tolerated both its white
sheep and its black sheep it is time to
do battle with the oppressive structures
that have been used to silence new ideas
if in my family I assert that there
might be as many as three revolutionary
Nobel quality ideas in one clutch how
many ideas might there be suppressed if
that is actually true how many people
are sitting on top of intellectual gold
that never got its chance to see the
light of day what I'd like to do is to
try to do battle with the disc to show
you that it exists to try to figure out
how it works and to try to show that the
tools that we currently have may be
powerful enough to defeat it this is the
actual purpose of the portal and I think
even if we lose some viewers and some
listeners even if people start to see
articles appearing that say how terrible
the show is and how it's trying to
foment some kind of unrest to hell with
them we are in an amazing position to
try to do something new and to stand up
for a lot of people who may have given
up on their own original ideas and to
try to spark a revolution because if I'm
right the disk has been sitting up on
top of some of our best and most hopeful
ideas for a way out of our economic
condemned rooms our military problems
ideas which have some chance of
delivering us to a much more interesting
and
tomorrow so I hope that this is gonna be
an unbelievable decade thank you guys
for sticking with it I'm sorry if this
was a little bit long but it was a lot
to say and it was heartfelt and quite
important to me to get it out and we
will return to trying to get you high
quality content either in the form of
instead of interviews which you've
become used to on the portal or perhaps
some new visual content that allows you
to understand ideas that would be very
difficult to communicate but for some
novel means of presentation we hope to
approach the community to try to
coordinate people who are eager to
contribute back into the program and
maybe get a little bit of a closer
relationship to our content going
forward maybe influence it a little bit
and we haven't figured out all of the
bugs so thanks for being part of the
initial experiment thanks for sticking
with us and we're looking forward to
being with you in the coming year in
decade ahead so you've been through the
portal for our first solo episode of
20/20 and be well everybody stay tuned
[Music]